<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses and the Royal Martyr, King Charles the First, parallel'd in a sermon preached on the 30th of January, 1683/4 in the Cathedral-Church of St. Peters, Exon. / by Tho. Long ...</title>
            <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13659327</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13659327</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101059</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49124)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101059)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 793:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moses and the Royal Martyr, King Charles the First, parallel'd in a sermon preached on the 30th of January, 1683/4 in the Cathedral-Church of St. Peters, Exon. / by Tho. Long ...</title>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. and E. Collins for Daniel Brown ... and are to be sold by Walter Davies ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Moses --  (Biblical leader)</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Deuteronomy XXXIV, 5 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101059:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101059:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOSES AND THE Royal Martyr (King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt) Parallel'd.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON Preached on the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> 1683/4.</p>
            <p>IN THE Cathedral-Church of St. <hi>Peters, EXON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>THO. LONG,</hi> one of the Prebendaries.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 6.29.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon in all his glory, was not like One of theſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> and <hi>F. Collins,</hi> for <hi>Daniel Brown</hi> at the <hi>black Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-bar;</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Walter Davies</hi> in <hi>Amen-corner.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101059:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101059:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>HENRY</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> One of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy-Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Great <hi>Devotion</hi> wherewith your Lordſhip indefatigably ſeeks to promote Works of <hi>Piety, Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and eſpecially the <hi>high veneration</hi> that you have for every <hi>little thing</hi> that concerns the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>ROYAL MARTYR,</hi> hath given me the preſumption of this <hi>Dedication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finding among ſome <hi>neglected Papers</hi> ſuch Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as ſeemed to retain (though but an obſcure) <hi>Character</hi> of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I carefully <hi>collected</hi> and <hi>compoſed</hi> them in this <hi>little Tablet.</hi> And though I well know that your Lordſhip hath a far <hi>more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Idea</hi> of that <hi>Beſt of Kings</hi> engraven on your heart; yet perceiving that this made a <hi>good im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> on a <hi>Loyal Audience</hi> at the firſt view, I have preſumed to make it <hi>more publick</hi> under your <hi>Lordſhips Name,</hi> which gives a <hi>value</hi> and <hi>luſtre</hi> to ſuch things as in themſelves are but of <hi>little worth:</hi> hoping that by this <hi>Recommendation</hi> of it, it may prove as an <hi>Amulet</hi> to <hi>confirm</hi> ſome in their <hi>Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>convince</hi> others of their <hi>Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty,</hi> by manifeſting to all, the <hi>incomparable Graces</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:101059:3"/>of that <hi>Man of God,</hi> and the <hi>unparallel'd Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of thoſe <hi>Sons of Belial,</hi> the <hi>Ignoramus's</hi> and <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natians</hi> that were <hi>Actors</hi> in that <hi>Tragedy;</hi> ſome of which ſtill <hi>ſurvive,</hi> and like the Devil himſelf, ſeek to <hi>draw others</hi> into the like <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi> with themſelves, and by <hi>another fatal Blow</hi> to deprive us of all thoſe <hi>Bleſſings Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> which by Gods wonderful Providence and Mercy we yet enjoy, and to reduce us to our <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Diſtractions</hi> and <hi>Confuſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it your Lorſhips <hi>publick Merit</hi> and <hi>Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> onely, but a particular and ſignal <hi>Favour to my ſelf,</hi> which (though <hi>forgotten</hi> by your ſelf, ſhall be ever thankfully <hi>commemorated</hi> by me) hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged me to this <hi>confident Addreſs.</hi> For in truth, I have been <hi>uneaſie</hi> and <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> with my ſelf, that I found no ſooner <hi>opportunity,</hi> nor as yet a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>demonſtration,</hi> of my <hi>Gratitude,</hi> and to let the World know what <hi>freedom of Acceſs,</hi> what <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of Countenance,</hi> and <hi>endearing Affability, Counſel,</hi> and <hi>Aſſiſtance,</hi> the meaneſt <hi>Clergy-man</hi> may hope for from ſo <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>munificent</hi> a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. In teſtimony whereof, I have done my ſelf the right, with your Lorſhips favour, to ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Exon, <date>Feb. <hi>12. 1683.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble and Obliged Servant, <hi>THO. LONG.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101059:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>DEUT. 34.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>So Moſes the ſervant of the Lord died in the land of Moab, according to the word of the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ST. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> being deſired by his friend <hi>Ceſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> to give him the Pattern of a <hi>holy life,</hi> tranſcribes the Hiſtory of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s <hi>Heroick Actions,</hi> and redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing them to <hi>Moral Duties,</hi> propoſeth them for his imitation. If ever the memorable Actions of that <hi>man of God</hi> were copied to the <hi>life,</hi> it was done by our ROYAL MARTYR, who ſo imitated whatever was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in <hi>Moſes,</hi> that it may be thought that <hi>God took of the Spirit of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and put it upon him.</hi> So <hi>like him</hi> he was in his <hi>life,</hi> that in his <hi>death</hi> he was not <hi>ſeparated.</hi> So he <hi>lived,</hi> and ſo he <hi>died,</hi> as <hi>Moſes the ſervant of the Lord died in the land of Moab, according to the word of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Text</hi> and the <hi>time</hi> requires me to run a <hi>Parallel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Royal Martyr;</hi> whoſe <hi>Obſequies</hi> we then duly celebrate, when we not onely <hi>bewail</hi> and <hi>detest</hi> that <hi>execrable Murther,</hi> and renounce thoſe <hi>Principles,</hi> and repent of thoſe <hi>Sins</hi> which betrayed that <hi>good man</hi> into the hands of <hi>deceitful and cruel meu,</hi> but do heartily endeavour to <hi>imitate</hi> that <hi>Chriſtian Example</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> which God by him hath commended unto us.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Parallel</hi> I ſhall extend,
<list>
                  <item>1. To his <hi>private</hi> and <hi>perſonal</hi> Excellencies, as he was <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. To his <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>political</hi> Capacity, as he was <hi>the ſervant of the Lord</hi> (i. e.) by way of Eminency, as he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101059:4"/>was <hi>a King in Jeſurun,</hi> Deut. 33.5. who ruled the People of God <hi>in the integrity of his heart,</hi> and <hi>with all his might.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And it is obſervable, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was born when there was a Generation of men that <hi>dealt ſubtily with the people of God;</hi> but God endued him with ſo much <hi>Patience,</hi> as well as <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Reſolution,</hi> that no difficulty was inſuperable to him.</p>
            <p>The firſt Grace that appeared in him was his <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Meekneſs;</hi> of which the Scripture teſtifieth, that <hi>he was the meekeſt man on the earth,</hi> Numb. 12.3. And though this were as another <hi>Vail</hi> on the face of <hi>our Moſes</hi> for a time, to obſcure the ſplendour of his Vertues, yet even that tended to his <hi>greater glory</hi> and <hi>admiration</hi> among ſuch as did more intimately converſe with him. He lived long in a <hi>retired condition,</hi> being <hi>educated in all the Wiſdom of the Egyptians,</hi> that might qualifie him for the <hi>Government</hi> to which God had deſigned him: yet his <hi>Meekneſs</hi> appeared firſt in a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of his own judgment; which though it were groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on <hi>ſtrong Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>mature Deliberation,</hi> yet he alway ſubmitted to ſuch as he thought better skilled in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sciences; though uſually when the <hi>Kings Opinion</hi> was <hi>neglected,</hi> and <hi>theirs followed,</hi> the ſucceſs failed: and when <hi>Moſes held up his hands, Iſrael prevailed; when he let them down, Amalek prevailed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Affability,</hi> another branch of <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> was ſuch, that the <hi>meaneſt Subject</hi> had a <hi>a gracious acceſs</hi> to him; nor needed there any <hi>Favourite</hi> or <hi>Advocate</hi> to mediate for him, ſave the <hi>juſtneſs of his Cauſe;</hi> which he would alway <hi>hear with great Patience,</hi> and <hi>determine with Prudence and Juſtice.</hi> And if at any time he perceived <hi>an Egyptian ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one of his Brethren,</hi> he would voluntarily <hi>interpoſe,</hi> and avenge the Oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>As for the Power which he exerciſed over his <hi>Paſſions,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101059:4"/>he was as much a <hi>King</hi> in that, as in any other Vertue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The <hi>Stoical Philoſophy</hi> never preſcribed a better <hi>Apathy</hi> than he practiſed; never diſcovering any <hi>Paſſion,</hi> but when the Cauſe of <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> was concerned: nor was he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver known to act any thing by way of <hi>revenge,</hi> though none was more <hi>provoked,</hi> and though he had <hi>Jus utriuſque gladii.</hi> His Enemies indeed made a <hi>ſelf-denying Ordinance,</hi> but none beſides himſelf did <hi>practiſe</hi> it. His <hi>moderation</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in words was ſo great, that he ſeldom <hi>ſpake unadviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his lips:</hi> and if he did, after inſufferable Affronts and Injuries, call his implacable Enemies <hi>Rebels,</hi> he did no more than <hi>Moſes,</hi> Numb. 20.10. <hi>Hear now, ye Rebels:</hi> and yet he mitigates the harſhneſs of that title with the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thite of a <hi>Religious Rebellion,</hi> and a <hi>miſguided Zeal;</hi> and prays for them in the words of our Saviour, <hi>Father, forgive them, they know not what they do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Innocency</hi> did ſo arm and fortifie him againſt all <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches</hi> and <hi>Injuries,</hi> that <hi>when he was reviled, he reviled not again; when he ſuffered, he threatned not;</hi> inſomuch that <hi>Philo</hi> ſays it was doubted of <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. whether he was a <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>mixt perſon.</hi> And without doubt our <hi>Moſes</hi> was in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s ſence, <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the Divine Nature.</hi> And if it be true what both Philoſophy and Divinity affirm, That <hi>he is a more valiant man that overcomes himſelf, than he that ſubdues many Cities, Alexander</hi> himſelf was not ſo great a <hi>Conqueror,</hi> who loſt all the <hi>glories</hi> of his <hi>former Conqueſts,</hi> by yielding to a <hi>baſe Luſt:</hi> but never did any <hi>rebel thought</hi> riſe up againſt the <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>our Moſes,</hi> which was not preſently and eaſily <hi>ſuppreſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that none of his Age better deſerved his Motto of <hi>More than Conqueror.</hi> And as he was an Abſolute Maſter of his <hi>Iraſcible,</hi> ſo of his <hi>Concupiſcible Appetites:</hi> for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he was of ſo <hi>ſound a Conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>equal temperature of body,</hi> that he might be naturally thought inclinable to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101059:5"/>and lived amidſt ſuch <hi>plenty</hi> and <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Temptations,</hi> that nothing but <hi>the grace of God</hi> could reſtrain him; that <hi>Grace was ſufficient</hi> to preſerve <hi>his righteous Soul,</hi> in the midſt of a <hi>Profane Generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A profeſſed Enemy he was to three <hi>great Debauchers</hi> of the Nation; <hi>Wine, Women,</hi> and <hi>Tobacco;</hi> ſo that, as <hi>Philo</hi> ſaid of <hi>Moſes, Frugalitatem colebat, ut nemo alius in univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum à deliciis abhorrens, animo malebat vivere quam corpori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Diet,</hi> he would <hi>feed heartily,</hi> but not <hi>nicely,</hi> nor <hi>intemperately:</hi> Hunger was his <hi>beſt Sauce,</hi> and he ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved his <hi>ſet-hours.</hi> He was none of thoſe Princes that brought a <hi>Wo</hi> to the Land, by <hi>riſing early to follow ſtrong drink, and continue till wine inflame them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.11. but guided himſelf and others by the wholſome Rules of <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance:</hi> And by theſe means he enjoyed that double Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, of a <hi>ſound mind</hi> in a <hi>healthy body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Apparel</hi> was ſutable to his mind; <hi>a plain man;</hi> no example of <hi>Expenſiveneſs,</hi> or aping <hi>new Faſhions:</hi> He thought it more neceſſary to adorn his <hi>Soul,</hi> on which he beſtowed more time and thoughtfulneſs than on his <hi>Body;</hi> by which onely he outſhined all the <hi>Gallantry</hi> of the Court; in which reſpect, ſhould we compare him with <hi>other Princes,</hi> it will be hard to find out a <hi>Parallel.</hi> For all circumſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, <hi>Solomon in all his glory was not like him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> conſidering the <hi>Temptations</hi> that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a perſon of <hi>his Complexion,</hi> he was <hi>another Joſeph,</hi> not onely a <hi>Worthy,</hi> but a <hi>Wonder of the World;</hi> inſomuch as he was ſuſpected of a <hi>natural Impotency</hi> and <hi>Frigidity,</hi> until God bleſſed him with <hi>a numerous Iſſue.</hi> Never was he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by his <hi>greateſt Enemies</hi> of any <hi>unclean Luſt.</hi> So that he deſerved that Character which the Hiſtorian required in <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Wife, <hi>Oportet uxorem Caeſaris non ſolum omni crimine, verum etiam omni criminis ſuſpicione vacare.</hi> He was above the <hi>ſuſpition</hi> of being a <hi>Wanton;</hi> yet to his death did the malice of his Enemies purſue his <hi>Reputation,</hi> giving order to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101059:5"/>ſome that were appointed, to ſee him <hi>diſſected,</hi> to enquire whether there were not a <hi>defect of nature</hi> in his body; who found, to their <hi>ſhame,</hi> that it was no <hi>decay of nature,</hi> but the <hi>ſtrength of Grace</hi> that reſtrained him. His <hi>conjugal love</hi> to his endeared <hi>Spouſe,</hi> whom her Enemies painted <hi>blacker</hi> than <hi>Moſes</hi>'s <hi>Egyptian Wife,</hi> admitted no muttering of <hi>Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> he was often condemned by them of <hi>too much,</hi> never for <hi>too little affection</hi> towards his Royal Spouſe; who, as ſhe could never incline his Heart to her <hi>Idols,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi>'s was, ſo his <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> together had undoubtedly wrought her to a <hi>better opinion</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> had not their <hi>vile Practices</hi> diſgraced that <hi>holy Profeſſion.</hi> Such was the <hi>Chaſtity</hi> of his holy Converſation, that he was coupled rather in <hi>the fear of God,</hi> than any <hi>carnal conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> So that his very <hi>Body,</hi> as well as the <hi>Soul,</hi> was <hi>the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole <hi>courſe of his life</hi> gives ſuch reputation to his <hi>dying words,</hi> that no ſober man can doubt of the truth of that Charge he gave the Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to tell her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>That his thoughts had never ſtrayed from her, and his love ſhould be the ſame to the laſt.</hi> And as <hi>Philo</hi> ſays of <hi>Moſes, Non quicquam ventri dabat praeter tributum naturae neceſſarium, nec voluptatam ſub ventre naſcentium niſi libero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cauſâ meminerat;</hi> though he lived amidſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> infinite Provocations, he <hi>reſiſted them all,</hi> and made every thing <hi>ſubſervient</hi> to <hi>Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is thought a ſufficient <hi>Panegyrick</hi> for ſome <hi>Princes,</hi> that they are <hi>ſine vitiis,</hi> without any predominant Vice; or at leaſt if they are conſpicuous for any <hi>one Vertue:</hi> but our <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> as he <hi>wanted</hi> all the <hi>Vices,</hi> ſo he <hi>had</hi> all the <hi>Vertues</hi> of his <hi>worthy Anceſtors,</hi> and even of <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf. He was ſo like <hi>Moſes,</hi> that he partook of the ſame <hi>infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:</hi> he was not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but of a <hi>ſlow ſpeech</hi> and <hi>ſtammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tongue;</hi> but that was abundantly ſupplied by a <hi>ſound Judgment</hi> and <hi>ſententious Elegancy.</hi> He did not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, make
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101059:6"/>
               <hi>long</hi> and <hi>popular Harangues,</hi> like the old Roman <hi>Gracchi,</hi> our <hi>Extempore</hi>-men, to lead the People by <hi>Noiſe</hi> and <hi>Clamour;</hi> but he could <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> teach them <hi>Maximes</hi> and <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion;</hi> and was, as <hi>Moſes, mighty in word and deed.</hi> For,</p>
            <p>In the next place, he was, as the Scripture teſtifies of <hi>Moſes, Learned in all the wiſdom of the Egyptians,</hi> Acts 7.22. Now the Sciences taught in <hi>Egypt</hi> were, as <hi>Philo</hi> ſays, <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meros &amp; Geometriam, Muſicam &amp; occultu Hieroglyphica, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipuè vero Mathematica.</hi> And for theſe, you have the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of an <hi>Adverſary,</hi> what a Proficient he was. <hi>Lilly</hi> in his Diſcourſe of <hi>Monarchy or no Monarchy,</hi> ſays, <hi>He had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular skill in Limning and Pictures; a good Mathematician, not unskilful in Muſick; well read in Divinity, excellently in Hiſtory, and no leſs in the Laws and Statutes of the Nation; of a quick and ſharp Conception; would write his mind ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly well, and in good Language and Stile: he would appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend a difference between party and party with great readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and methodize a long matter, and contract it in few lines: Inſomuch that I have heard Sir</hi> Robert Holborn <hi>oft ſay, he had a quicker Conception, and would eaſier underſtand a Caſe in Law, and with more ſharpneſs drive the matter to a head, than any of the Privy-Council: and when the King was not at the Council, Sir</hi> Robert <hi>cared not to be there. He had alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other ſpecial Gifts, the Gift of Patience, ſo that if any offered him a long diſcourſe, he would without any interruption or diſtate hear it out. He had exquiſite judgment by the eye, to diſcover the vertuous from the wanton; and honoured ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous men. He was nothing at all given to Luxury, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme ſober in his Food and Apparel. He would argue logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and frame his Argument artificially,</hi> &amp;c. The like we have from <hi>another,</hi> though <hi>bitter Enemy</hi> of his, and a <hi>Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor</hi> againſt him at his Tryal, <hi>Cooke,</hi> in his <hi>Apologie</hi> for their proceedings againſt him, <hi>p.</hi> 35. <hi>He was well known</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to be a hard Student in his younger days—He had more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101059:6"/>and dexterity in State-affairs undoubtedly, than all the Kings in Chriſtendom; and for his Parts, if they had been ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified</hi> (ſaid that unſanctified wretch) <hi>he was another Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> This Teſtimony being true, how ſharply were they to be <hi>rebuked</hi> that perſecuted him to death!</p>
            <p>But we muſt <hi>ſearch farther,</hi> to find out the Excellencies of <hi>Moſes. Diodorus Siculus</hi> notes, that he was bred up in <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Court, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t urbanitatem, Elegantiam, Liberalitatem, aliaſque virtutes Regias quaſi Rector populi futurus addiſceret.</hi> And though <hi>our Moſes</hi> were a <hi>Nonſuch</hi> in all theſe, yet all theſe were nothing in reſpect of that Wiſdom which he was taught of God. Though his whole life was no more than what <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpent in his retirement, yet he attained to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable meaſure of all <hi>uſeful knowledge.</hi> For as he <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> many <hi>good Authors</hi> throughout with his <hi>own hand,</hi> ſo he tranſcribed their <hi>choice Precepts</hi> into his <hi>heart.</hi> So <hi>ſtudious</hi> and <hi>reſerved</hi> he was, that Prince <hi>Henry</hi> took the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Cap and put it on his head, ſaying, <hi>If I live,</hi> Charles, <hi>I'll make thee Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury. Being at the age of thirteen years, on <hi>Eaſter-Munday</hi> 1613. he was <hi>ſtrictly examined</hi> in order to his <hi>Confirmation,</hi> by the Archbiſhop and the Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells;</hi> as Dr. <hi>Hackwel</hi> his Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who was preſent, and heard his Anſwers, which gave great ſatisfaction to them all, relateth. On which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Doctor wrote his Treatiſe of <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When his Father King <hi>James</hi> ſent him to <hi>Spain,</hi> he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Attendants not to <hi>begin Diſputes</hi> concerning Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>But if you be engaged, let</hi> George, ſaith the King, <hi>hold the Concluſion, and</hi> Charles <hi>will maintain the Premiſes; for I dare venture him againſt the beſt ſtudied Divine of them all.</hi> Nor was his <hi>Learning</hi> confined to <hi>one part,</hi> but he digeſted <hi>all the Wiſdom</hi> of his Age. His <hi>Pen</hi> was incomparably the moſt <hi>Princely,</hi> and <hi>beſt poliſhed</hi> in his time. In the <hi>Camp,</hi> none diſcourſed more like a <hi>Souldier;</hi> in the <hi>Council,</hi> none ſo like a <hi>Senator:</hi> among the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> as an <hi>Oracle;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101059:7"/>the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as another <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> He always <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed over</hi> his Enemies, as <hi>Spartianus</hi> ſays of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Trajan</hi> in Imagine; overthrowing them by his <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> whom he could not reach by his <hi>Arms.</hi> His <hi>Pen</hi> did what his <hi>Sword</hi> could not do; for that, like <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s Arrows, was never employed in vain.</p>
            <p>In his Deliberations with his <hi>Council,</hi> he led them by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,</hi> not by <hi>Authority:</hi> and though he left them to the liberty of their <hi>own Determinations,</hi> yet were they never ſo <hi>ſucceſsful,</hi> as when <hi>his Majeſties advice</hi> was followed: inſomuch as they all ſaid, <hi>If he had been a Counſellor to any other Prince, he had been eſteemed as an Oracle.</hi> When his Secretaries had drawn up <hi>publick Diſpatches</hi> for <hi>foreign Princes,</hi> he would often take the Pen in hand, and ſaying pleaſantly, <hi>I am a pretty good Cobler,</hi> would make ſuch <hi>advantageous al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations</hi> both in <hi>words</hi> and <hi>matter,</hi> as were approved by them all. So that even <hi>his Enemies</hi> would ſay, <hi>If he had not been born to be a King, no man deſerved it better than he:</hi> which Sir <hi>H. Martin</hi> teſtified of him, in that Houſe where the Queſtion was propoſed in favour of <hi>Cromwel, Whether they ſhould have a King or no King. If we muſt have a King</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I had rather have him than any Gentleman in the Nation.</hi> So that it ſeems he had no other fault, than that <hi>he was born to be a King, and God had anointed him above his fellows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which brings me to the <hi>ſecond part</hi> of the <hi>Parallel;</hi> How like our <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> was to <hi>Moſes</hi> in his <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Capacity,</hi> as he was <hi>the ſervant of the Lord;</hi> for ſo is the King call'd, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gods Minſter</hi> or <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> by way of eminence, and immediate relation; <hi>the man of God,</hi> 1 Chron. 23.14. <hi>The man of Gods right hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Regalia</hi> which both adorn and ſupport the <hi>Throne,</hi> are <hi>Mercy and Truth,</hi> which <hi>preſerve</hi> the King, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.28. &amp; <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.14. <hi>The king that faithfully judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the poor, his throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101059:7"/>
            <p>And firſt, of his <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Clemency,</hi> which, as the <hi>holy Oyl,</hi> kept his Crown <hi>freſh</hi> and <hi>fragrant,</hi> and added a <hi>beauty</hi> to all the <hi>other Jewels</hi> that adorned it. In all the former Vertues he excelled <hi>others,</hi> in this he exceeded himſelf: <hi>Like the Oyntment on the head of Moſes, it ran down to the skirts of his Garment,</hi> to the <hi>meaneſt of his Subjects,</hi> and the <hi>moſt malicious of his Enemies.</hi> If it be poſſible that any Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue can be in <hi>exceſs,</hi> this of <hi>Clemency</hi> was ſo in him. <hi>I thank God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I never found but my Pity was above my Anger: nor have my Paſſions ever ſo prevailed againſt me, as to exclude my compaſſionate Prayers for them whom devout er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, more than their own malice, have betrayed to a Religious Rebellion.</hi> Here is <hi>Charity</hi> indeed, that could <hi>cover ſuch a multitude of ſins!</hi> His uſual Prayer for them was, <hi>That Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance might be their greateſt puniſhment.</hi> Being asked by Colonel <hi>Hammond</hi> his Jaylor, what <hi>regret</hi> his Spirit had againſt his <hi>Enemies;</hi> he anſwered, <hi>I can forgive them, Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, with as good an appetite, as ever I eat my meat after hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; and that I'll aſſure you was no ſmall one. Moſes</hi> in his charity did not onely <hi>wiſh that all the people were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> but that God would <hi>blot him out of the book of life,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Legiſlaturae,</hi> or <hi>vitae temporalis</hi>) ſo the <hi>people</hi> might be <hi>ſpared. To procure a Calm,</hi> ſays the Royal Martyr, <hi>I could be content to be the</hi> Jonas <hi>thrown over board.</hi> Next to his <hi>Wife and Children,</hi> he profeſt to <hi>love his Enemies deareſt:</hi> and ſo far was he from ſeeking to deſtroy the <hi>living,</hi> that he wiſht he could <hi>revive</hi> them that were <hi>dead.</hi> He <hi>gave</hi> ſo long, till his Enemies left him nothing more for them to <hi>ask,</hi> or him to <hi>grant:</hi> he gave not onely <hi>to the one half,</hi> but the <hi>whole of his Kingdom.</hi> He <hi>forgave</hi> and <hi>pardoned</hi> thoſe who were <hi>ſelf-condemned,</hi> and had never charity enough to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>themſelves,</hi> but like <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> thought their <hi>Murthers</hi> and <hi>Treaſons greater than could be forgiven.</hi> He <hi>pardoned</hi> thoſe, whom God himſelf hath ſaid <hi>he will never pardon,</hi> ſuch as continued <hi>obſtinately</hi> to <hi>offend</hi> out of <hi>mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101059:8"/>wickedneſs.</hi> Yet did the Charity of <hi>Moſes</hi> not onely pordon that <hi>ſtiff-necked people</hi> himſelf, but kept <hi>wreſtling with God</hi> to pardon them alſo. <hi>Let me alone, that I may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, and I will make of thee a great Nation:</hi> Yet ſtill <hi>Moſes prayed</hi> and <hi>prevailed,</hi> Exod. 32.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is ſaid of Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> that <hi>the way to make him a friend, was to do him an injury.</hi> The <hi>leſs</hi> our <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> was beloved by his Enemies, the <hi>more</hi> he loved and pitied them. Though the moſt <hi>tender mercies</hi> of his <hi>Enemies</hi> towards him were <hi>very cruelty,</hi> his <hi>greateſt cruelty</hi> towards them, was his <hi>too tender mercy,</hi> which they <hi>ungrateful wretches</hi> ſo abuſed, as to turn his <hi>Bounty</hi> into <hi>Laſciviouſneſs, kicking</hi> at <hi>thoſe bowels</hi> that <hi>yearned</hi> towards them, and turning his <hi>Acts of free and undeſerved Grace,</hi> into <hi>ſins of Preſumption:</hi> for ſome of them did ſay, <hi>They knew the King had Charity enough to forgive them all;</hi> as indeed he did, to the laſt moment of his life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> His <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> was another <hi>Regale.</hi> No man, woman, or child could ever complain, of any thing taken from them by <hi>force</hi> or <hi>fraud</hi> in which they had a right: <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Truth met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>kiſſed each other; Righteouſneſs and Peace like a mighty ſtream flowed thorough the Land,</hi> and <hi>made glad the City of God;</hi> and ſo ſecured the Nation in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Plenty,</hi> as the Waters that compaſs the Land round about. No drop of Bloud was ſhed during ſeventeen years of his <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturbed Reign,</hi> ſave of an <hi>ear or two</hi> of ſuch <hi>turbulent men,</hi> who ſurvived to be the Authors of ſhedding <hi>whole Rivers</hi> of <hi>more innocent bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the third <hi>Regale,</hi> which is <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs;</hi> he was, <hi>as Moſes, faithful in all Gods houſe;</hi> Deo, Sacerdotio, Populo: To <hi>God,</hi> to his <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>People:</hi> not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting willingly any <hi>pin</hi> to be wanting that was for <hi>neceſſary</hi> or <hi>decent uſe</hi> in all the <hi>Tabernacles</hi> of the Lord; nor enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing but what was <hi>agreeable to the pattern in the Mount,</hi> (i. e.) to <hi>the Word of God,</hi> and <hi>primitive practice.</hi> He
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101059:8"/>was indeed <hi>a Nurſing Father</hi> to the Church of God; he <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried</hi> it in his <hi>boſom,</hi> and <hi>ingraved</hi> it on his heart. His care was, that the <hi>Daughter of Sion</hi> might not onely be <hi>all glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous within,</hi> but that her <hi>Garments</hi> might be of <hi>fine Needle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work.</hi> So zealous was he to preſerve her <hi>Revenues,</hi> that if it were true of any ſince our Saviours time, it was true of him, <hi>The zeal of Gods houſe did conſume him.</hi> His love to the <hi>Church</hi> as far exceeded that of <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Jonathan,</hi> as that <hi>ſurpaſſed the love of women.</hi> He offered to <hi>ſell</hi> part of the <hi>Crown-lands,</hi> to <hi>preſerve</hi> thoſe of the <hi>Church;</hi> which that <hi>ſcurrilous Milton</hi> called his <hi>Epheſian Goddeſs,</hi> perceiving that he was willing to <hi>ſacrifice his life</hi> and <hi>all</hi> for its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity: for if he would have conſented to the <hi>Alienation</hi> of <hi>thoſe Lands,</hi> he might have <hi>patcht up a Peace</hi> with his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and in probability have <hi>ſaved his life:</hi> but no <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> of his <hi>Favourites,</hi> no <hi>neceſſities</hi> of his <hi>own,</hi> could gain his conſent to any <hi>Sacrilegious Act. Tell me not</hi> (ſaid he to a great Counſellor) <hi>what I may do to ſave my life, but what I may do with a ſafe Conſcience: I have done what I can to the ſaving of my life, without loſing my Soul: I can do, I will do no more; Gods will be done: I ſhall never think my ſelf leſs than my ſelf, while I am able to preſerve the integrity of my Conſcience: Leave me that, and let what will befal me: I ſhall chuſe any affliction, rather than ſin.</hi> And again, <hi>Though I am ſenſible enough of the danger that attends my care of the Church, yet I am reſolved to defend it, or make it my Tomb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone.</hi> — Nimirum hoc eſt regnare.</p>
            <p>Nor was he careful onely to preſerve the Church during his <hi>own life,</hi> but provided for its proſperity <hi>after his death.</hi> Charging his <hi>deareſt Son,</hi> that <hi>he ſhould not let his heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the leaſt check or diſſatisfaction againſt the Church, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem any thing little or deſpicable, ſo as not ſpeedily to ſuppreſs Errours and Schiſms.</hi> Nor can any man impute theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions to his <hi>Wilfulneſs,</hi> but <hi>Conſcience,</hi> who ſhall conſider with what <hi>ſtrength of Argument</hi> he defended the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101059:9"/>its Adverſaries of all ſorts. His diſcourſe with the Marqueſs of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> (though printed to his great diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and but partially related) ſhewed his <hi>Learning</hi> in <hi>Popiſh Controverſies,</hi> and his <hi>averſion</hi> from <hi>that Perſwaſion.</hi> His Papers to <hi>Henderſon</hi> ſhew his acquaintance with the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Modern Divines</hi> in our preſent Controverſies. He alone diſputed a whole day in the <hi>Iſle of Wight</hi> (concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Church-affairs</hi> eſpecially) on the <hi>Propoſitions</hi> ſent him, againſt fifteen <hi>Counſellors</hi> and four <hi>Divines,</hi> to the <hi>Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of them all; who coming <hi>prejudiced</hi> againſt him, as a man of <hi>ſlender parts,</hi> went away <hi>admiring</hi> how he became ſo <hi>learned;</hi> and willing they were <hi>his Conceſſions might have been admitted as a ground to treat of Peace.</hi> Mr. <hi>Vines,</hi> the beſt Diſputant of the Party, ſaid <hi>he was ſorry the King was not better underſtood; for he thought him the beſt Divine of any Lay-man in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>Now who can diſtruſt the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>fidelity</hi> of ſuch a King towards his <hi>Subjects,</hi> that was ſo <hi>ſtedfaſt</hi> and <hi>faithful</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church?</hi> the love of <hi>God</hi> and of our <hi>Brethren</hi> being inſeparable. His many <hi>Proteſtations of his innocency</hi> as to the things whereof his Enemies accuſed him, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as to <hi>Poper,</hi> yat <hi>York</hi> in the head of his Army, at <hi>Oxford</hi> upon taking the Holy Sacrament at the hands of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and in this place (St. <hi>Peters, Exon</hi>) after the Defeat of <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s Army in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> and at ſeveral other places, being compared with his great <hi>Knowledge, Candor,</hi> and <hi>Integrity,</hi> were enough to convince any but ſuch <hi>hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Pharachs</hi> and <hi>Egyptians</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> had to deal with.</p>
            <p>So that his Enemies moſt notoriouſly <hi>condemned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> when they ſo falſly <hi>accuſed him</hi> of <hi>Inconſtancy</hi> in the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Religion;</hi> which they ſo quickly <hi>razed to the very foundation</hi> with their <hi>Swords,</hi> and he ſo <hi>reſolutely defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> with his <hi>laſt bloud.</hi> But as neither the Divinity of our Saviour's <hi>Perſon, Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> nor his <hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Works</hi> could ſatisfie the <hi>unbelieving Jews,</hi> who were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101059:9"/>to put him to death; ſo could neither the <hi>Piety of his life,</hi> his <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>innumerable Condeſcentions</hi> and <hi>Meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for Peace</hi> reſtrain theſe <hi>Jewiſh Infidels</hi> from imbruing their hands in his <hi>innocent Bloud,</hi> and <hi>entailing</hi> the <hi>guilt</hi> thereof <hi>on them and their children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>great man</hi> did not receive his Religion by <hi>Tradition</hi> from his <hi>Fathers,</hi> or by an <hi>implicit Faith</hi> in his <hi>Teachers</hi> (as <hi>moſt men</hi> now do; which makes them ſo <hi>wavering</hi> and <hi>unſtable,</hi> leaping from one <hi>Perſwaſion</hi> to another:) he ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into the <hi>fundamental grounds</hi> and <hi>principles;</hi> he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and confuted all the <hi>Objections</hi> againſt it; and from hence it was that he ſtood as a <hi>Temple built upon a Rock,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable, notwithſtanding all his and its Adverſaries <hi>violent Aſſaults.</hi> So that the <hi>beſt Reformed Church</hi> in the World <hi>ſtood and fell</hi> with him; and, bleſſed be God, hath had a <hi>Reſurrection</hi> with his <hi>Son</hi> our <hi>dear Soveraign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his <hi>conſtant attendance</hi> on the <hi>Publick Worſhip,</hi> which he duly frequented, he performed that with that <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Devotion</hi> and <hi>Reverence,</hi> without which <hi>all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is in vain.</hi> And if at any time he had omitted his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>praying twice a day,</hi> which he ſcarce ever did in all the time of <hi>War,</hi> conſecrating ſome place as a <hi>Chappel</hi> in the <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Field;</hi> ſo <hi>tender</hi> was his Spirit, that he exacted it of himſelf at <hi>anothor time.</hi> As <hi>Philo</hi> obſerves of <hi>Moſes, Si quando ab officio defuiſſet, ſeverè à ſe paenas exigebat.</hi> He <hi>had</hi> that <hi>tenderneſs of Conſcience</hi> which was onely <hi>talked of</hi> by others: for as ſoon as the <hi>wrath</hi> of God was <hi>gone out</hi> againſt the Land, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> he <hi>ran and ſtood in the gap,</hi> and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf with <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Supplications</hi> to divert the wrath of God. And for his <hi>ſecret Meditations</hi> and <hi>Vows,</hi> he hath raiſed ſuch a <hi>Monument</hi> to himſelf, and given ſuch an <hi>Example</hi> to the World, as all men may <hi>admire,</hi> but few or none can <hi>imitate.</hi> King <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt ſaid, that <hi>of all Books in the World, next to that of the Goſpel, he would have that of</hi> Moſes <hi>his Pentateuch to be preſerved.</hi> And indeed thoſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101059:10"/>Books are, as <hi>Philo</hi> ſays, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. theſe are the onely Records of the Creation and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous providence of God, wherein alſo the fundamentals of all Laws are preſerved. And next to <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> and the <hi>Records of the Church,</hi> there is no Book ſavours ſo much of <hi>Divine Rhetorick,</hi> and the <hi>Primitive Spirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion,</hi> as the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth. I have ſeen <hi>his Majeſties Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture</hi> drawn in the <hi>Text</hi> of <hi>David's Pſalms;</hi> a fit ſhadow for the <hi>Devotion</hi> of his Soul: but this which was drawn by his own <hi>unimitable Pen,</hi> will be a <hi>more laſting Monument,</hi> and give him a <hi>better Immortality</hi> than all the <hi>Regal Memoirs</hi> of the beſt-deſerving Princes: by this, as <hi>Sampſon,</hi> he <hi>conquered more at his death, than he had done in all his life-time. Vota dabant, quae bella negarunt;</hi> his <hi>Pen</hi> obtained what his <hi>Sword</hi> could not. As none but <hi>Caeſar</hi> was fit to write his own Comment, ſo the <hi>King</hi> did it in ſuch a <hi>ſtile,</hi> as will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate his <hi>Fame</hi> to the end of the World. And for my part, I ſhall like it the better, for that which that <hi>ſcurrilous Milton</hi> ſaid to defame it, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>his Party admired it, and were ſtricken with ſuch blindneſs, as next to the darkneſs of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, happened not to any people more groſs or miſleading.</hi> For which ſaying perhaps it was, that <hi>he himſelf</hi> was ſmitten with <hi>blindneſs</hi> long before his death. I conclude this point of the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>fidelity</hi> of <hi>our Moſes,</hi> with that which <hi>Philo</hi> ſays of his: <hi>Qualis erat Oratio, talis erat vita, ut in inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento muſico nil diſcrepavit, mentem actis exprimens, facta di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis accommodans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not preſume to extend my <hi>Parallel</hi> between <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> for <hi>working of Miracles;</hi> though God gave him ſuch a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>gift of healing,</hi> as was very <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful,</hi> and <hi>highly beneficial</hi> to the Nation, in the curing of thouſands that were otherwiſe incurable. But that which cauſeth me to mention this, was that <hi>Cure</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> wrought upon <hi>Miriam,</hi> who was troubled with a kind of <hi>Kings Evil,</hi> being ſmitten with a <hi>Leproſie</hi> ſomewhat like it,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101059:10"/>for her <hi>murmuring againſt Moſes;</hi> but was cured by his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Moſes cryed to the Lord, ſaying, Heal her now, O God, I beſeech thee.</hi> And when the rude Souldiers that guarded his Majeſty denied a poor afflicted woman that was very importunate to have acceſs to him, deriding her as a ſuperſtitious woman; the <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> obſerving and pitying her condition, told her, <hi>Though he could not touch her, he would pray to God to heal her:</hi> and ſhe went to her home, and was healed. But to return,</p>
            <p>But theſe <hi>Supporters</hi> of the <hi>Royal Throne,</hi> his Kingdoms were preſerved in <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Proſperity</hi> for near ſeventeen years together: there was no <hi>decay of Trade,</hi> no <hi>leading into Captivity,</hi> no <hi>Wars nor rumors of Wars</hi> among us. The <hi>King himſelf</hi> was the <hi>greateſt ſufferer,</hi> being left in ſome <hi>ſtraights,</hi> and engaged in <hi>expenſive affairs</hi> by his Father: which his Adverſaries taking notice of, inſtead of <hi>eaſing him</hi> by timely <hi>ſupplies,</hi> they <hi>adde to it</hi> by <hi>murmurings,</hi> and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the old Quarrel between the <hi>Kings Prerogative</hi> and the <hi>Priviledges of the People.</hi> For the deciſion of which, <hi>our Moſes</hi> ſummons an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Heads</hi> of the People, hoping that they would <hi>take part of the burden</hi> of the Government from his ſhoulders, which was <hi>too heavy for him to bear alone,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> complained to God, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 14. wherefore by <hi>Gods decree</hi> he calls the <hi>Elders of the people to ſtand with him,</hi> v. 16. but <hi>v.</hi> 26. we hear of <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad,</hi> two <hi>Field-Chaplains</hi> that <hi>ſeparated</hi> from the Tabernacle, and <hi>propheſied in the Camp</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam</hi> alſo, <hi>ch.</hi> 12. 1. a zealous woman, <hi>ſpake againſt Moſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of an Ethiopian woman whom Moſes had married:</hi> whom God reproved, <hi>v.</hi> 7. teſtifying of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that <hi>he was faithful in all his houſe;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 8. ſaying, <hi>How were ye not afraid to ſpeak againſt my ſervant Moſes?</hi> And this <hi>Leven,</hi> though but a <hi>little</hi> at firſt, <hi>fermented the whole lump:</hi> for, <hi>ch.</hi> 16. 1. <hi>Corah, Dathan, and Abiram, with</hi> 250 <hi>Princes of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, famous in the Congregation, men of renown,</hi> began to make
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101059:11"/>
               <hi>ſet Speeches</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> and ſo incenſed the people, that, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſays, <hi>they came with a confuſed tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult to apprehend and ſtone Moſes, and with noiſe and uproar they came to the very door of the Tabernacle where Moſes was, crying out, that the Tyrant was to be cut off, and the people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from thraldom, having great burdens laid on them. Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> come alſo with their <hi>armed Servants</hi> to reſiſt <hi>Moſes</hi> in caſe of <hi>force.</hi> And now <hi>Corah,</hi> a man of <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Eloquence,</hi> talks aloud, That <hi>Moſes</hi> had <hi>lifted up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> without any Commiſſion above the People, thinking to exerciſe an <hi>Arbitrary power</hi> over them, who were <hi>all holy,</hi> and to whom, as <hi>Saints,</hi> the power of <hi>Dominion</hi> did belong: and accuſed them as <hi>men of bloud,</hi> v. 41. <hi>Ye have ſlain the people of the Lord;</hi> though as yet neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor <hi>Aaron</hi> had uſed any other weapons but their <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> to appeaſe the <hi>rage of the people,</hi> and to turn away the <hi>wrath of God</hi> from them. But from this time began the <hi>Affliction</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom God ſeemed to have raiſed up to this very end, that he might ſhew in him the <hi>power of his grace;</hi> how able he is to ſupport a <hi>weak veſſel,</hi> amidſt an <hi>ocean of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles:</hi> for as <hi>Philo</hi> ſays of <hi>Moſes, Tota vita Moſis Martyrium Deo reddidit,</hi> his whole life was but a Martyrdom: from the time that he was <hi>drawn out</hi> of the <hi>Bulruſhes</hi> of <hi>Tweed,</hi> where he was expoſed in a languiſhing condition, till he died on Mount <hi>Abarim,</hi> before his <hi>Royal Palace;</hi> his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies made him to <hi>paſs through fire and water</hi> more than <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times,</hi> that he might be as <hi>tryed Gold,</hi> the more precious and ſplendid: for though, as <hi>Moſes</hi> Buſh, he was <hi>ſtill bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> yet <hi>was he not conſumed;</hi> but they made him, in a <hi>better ſence</hi> than ever they intended, <hi>a glorious King.</hi> Non eripit terrena, qui regna dat Coeleſtia.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>our Moſes</hi> hath another <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Armies</hi> to deal with, who by <hi>vile arts</hi> had <hi>ſtollen the hearts of the people</hi> from <hi>him,</hi> and were deaf to all his <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages</hi> and <hi>Intreaties</hi> for <hi>Peace;</hi> God having given them up
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101059:11"/>to the <hi>hardneſs of their hearts,</hi> with a <hi>Quis conſtituit te, Who made thee a Judge and a Ruler over us?</hi> Acts 7.27. They had wreſted the <hi>Rod of Government</hi> out of his hands; and being <hi>caſt to the ground,</hi> it became a <hi>Serpent;</hi> and all the <hi>Plagues of Egypt</hi> which befel the <hi>obdurate people,</hi> could not reclaim them. The <hi>rivers were turned into bloud,</hi> Exod. 7.20. And <hi>murmuring ſeditious Libels</hi> and <hi>Declarations,</hi> like the <hi>Frogs of Egypt,</hi> were <hi>croaking</hi> in every <hi>houſe</hi> and <hi>chamber,</hi> ch. 8. 6. <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> like <hi>ſwarms of biting Lice and Flyes,</hi> filled the Land, <hi>ch.</hi> 8. 17. 24. A grievous <hi>Murrain</hi> there was upon the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> ch. 9. 3. and <hi>Botches,</hi> and <hi>Blains,</hi> and <hi>Peſtilence</hi> upon <hi>men,</hi> ch. 9. 10. The <hi>Cannons</hi> and <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering-pieces</hi> were as loud and fatal as the <hi>Thunder and ſtorms of Hail,</hi> v. 23. And <hi>deſtroying Souldiers,</hi> like <hi>Armies of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts, covered the face of the land, confuming every herb, and all the fruit of the trees.</hi> And though <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaw and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that <hi>theſe Plagues</hi> would deſtroy him and his ſervants, yet would he not ſubmit to God, and his <hi>ſervant Moſes,</hi> to <hi>let the people go and ſerve their God.</hi> But <hi>mercenary Preachers,</hi> like ſo many <hi>Balaams</hi> and <hi>Magicians,</hi> were ſtill hired to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and blaſpheme <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Moſes their King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein indeed the <hi>ſufferings</hi> of the <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> exceeded thoſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> That they were <hi>Egyptians</hi> who thus op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <hi>Moſes,</hi> but they were <hi>his own natural,</hi> or rather <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Subjects,</hi> that dealt thus cruelly with our <hi>Royal Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr;</hi> in whom not onely all the ſufferings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but of all the <hi>Martyrs</hi> met, to <hi>afflict</hi> and <hi>conſume</hi> him. For he was not onely deprived of all the comforts of his <hi>Life, Wife</hi> and <hi>Children, Counſellors</hi> and <hi>Chaplains,</hi> as if they intended to deſtroy his <hi>Soul</hi> as well as his <hi>body;</hi> but moreover he had <hi>tryal of cruel mockings,</hi> of <hi>bonds and impriſonment:</hi> he was <hi>tempted</hi> too; but <hi>would not accept deliverance</hi> by betraying the <hi>Cauſe of God</hi> and his <hi>Church:</hi> and at laſt <hi>was ſawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder,</hi> and <hi>ſlain with the ſword,</hi> Heb. 11.36. And to ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate all theſe <hi>Impieties,</hi> I may adde, that they were done to him <hi>of whom the world was not worthy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101059:12"/>
            <p>He ſuffered in his <hi>Body,</hi> being not allowed <hi>convenient Food and Raiment,</hi> as if they would try whether he could live by <hi>Manna</hi> and <hi>Miracle:</hi> He was forced to <hi>borrow money</hi> to buy him <hi>bread;</hi> and wanting <hi>Linen</hi> when he was at <hi>Holdenby,</hi> being adviſed to make his caſe known to <hi>them at Weſtminſter,</hi> he ſaid, he <hi>would not give them the ſatisfaction of knowing his wants.</hi> Next, he ſuffered in his <hi>good name,</hi> as if they would <hi>bury him alive</hi> under <hi>a heap of Reproaches;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they reported him to be an <hi>eaſie</hi> and <hi>miſguided fool,</hi> led away by <hi>wicked Counſellors;</hi> and anon, as an <hi>obſtinate</hi> and <hi>cruel Tyrant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He <hi>died</hi> often as a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> when he <hi>ſurvived</hi> as a <hi>man;</hi> that at laſt he might endure <hi>a double Martyrdom;</hi> and die as his Saviour did, with a <hi>Crown of Thorns on his head,</hi> and a <hi>Reed in his hand,</hi> while they that crucified him <hi>bowed before him, and mocked him.</hi> And as if this Impiety were not great enough, they mock the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Land,</hi> by ſetting up the <hi>higheſt Court of Injuſtice</hi> that ever was heard of in the world. With great Reaſon therefore and undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Reſolution he <hi>denied their Authority;</hi> to which if he had ſubmitted, they would have <hi>eſtabliſhed Iniquity by a Law,</hi> and urged the <hi>Kings ſubmiſſion</hi> againſt the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of any of his Subjects. He therefore required a <hi>Reaſon</hi> of their uſurping that Authority over him. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> told him, <hi>The Vote of the Commons was the Reaſon of the Nation:</hi> againſt which, when the King offered his <hi>Reaſons, Bradſhaw</hi> replied. <hi>That Reaſon was not to be heard againſt the highest Judicature.</hi> To which the King replying, <hi>Shew me that Count where Reaſon is not to be heard;</hi> he anſwered, <hi>We ſhew it here, the Commons of England:</hi> ſo evident it is that they had loſt their <hi>Reaſon</hi> as well as their <hi>Religion,</hi> and had bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed all <hi>fear of God</hi> with the <hi>Reverence of man.</hi> This is that <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> who a little before, ſome ſay but three weeks, when he was made a Serjeant at Law, <hi>took the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance,</hi> that at the ſame time he might condemn himſelf with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101059:12"/>
               <hi>Perjury,</hi> when he <hi>betrayed his Maſter.</hi> Yet all theſe <hi>Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities</hi> drew onely ſome <hi>ſmiles of Indignation;</hi> and <hi>pitying</hi> of thoſe unreaſonable and cruel men; and ſo he received that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gly Sentence,</hi> as he call'd it, as the <hi>Primitive Martyrs</hi> were wont to do, with a <hi>Deo gratias;</hi> bleſſing God, that as he had ſent him <hi>Afflictions,</hi> ſo he had given him <hi>Patience</hi> to endure them. And now they make haſte to <hi>lead him away,</hi> and <hi>crucifie him:</hi> and that he might yet be more like his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, one of the <hi>rude Souldiers</hi> that guarded him <hi>ſpit in his face;</hi> which he meekly wiping off, ſaid, <hi>My Saviour ſuffered more for my ſake.</hi> The Sunday before his death, a Guard of <hi>barbarous Souldiers</hi> were crowded into his Chamber, <hi>drinking</hi> and <hi>ſmoaking Tobacco,</hi> to which he had a natural an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy, <hi>curſing</hi> and <hi>upbraiding him</hi> to his face: ſo that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> was not ſo ill at eaſe in the <hi>Lions Den,</hi> as his <hi>righteous Soul</hi> among thoſe <hi>men of Belial.</hi> And to diſturb him yet more, he was lodged ſo near the <hi>place of Execution,</hi> that he might hear every ſtroak of thoſe who wrought all night on the Scaffold. <hi>Peters</hi> and <hi>Goodwin,</hi> two <hi>Army-Chaplains,</hi> would have given him <hi>Vinegar and Gall to drink,</hi> in the words of <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14.18, 19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but a <hi>better Angel</hi> was ſent from Heaven with a <hi>Cup of Conſolation:</hi> for on the very day of his death was read the Hiſtory of our Saviours Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. and thanking the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> who then miniſtred unto him, for his <hi>choice of ſo ſeaſonable a Leſſon,</hi> the Biſhop told him it was <hi>not by his choice, but by the courſe and order of the Church, that that Leſſon was appointed to be read;</hi> which he owned as a gracious providence and favour from his God. Nor were they more haſty for <hi>his Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> than he was for a <hi>deliverance from them:</hi> for he deſired the Guard to <hi>mend their pace,</hi> aſſuring them, that <hi>he never marched in the head of any Army with better courage to fight for his Earthly, than he did now for the Heavenly Crown.</hi> He was not appaled when he ſaw a <hi>red Sea</hi> before him, and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Egyptians</hi> on every ſide: he did not, as <hi>Moſes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101059:13"/>quake and fear,</hi> but was more concerned for <hi>his Murtherers</hi> than for <hi>himſelf.</hi> And <hi>Philo</hi> ſays of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Non calligavit oculus, nec mutatus eſt Splendor Gratiae vultus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.7. <hi>his eye</hi> and <hi>countenance</hi> retained the ſame <hi>Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Splendor</hi> on the <hi>Scaffold,</hi> as on the <hi>Throne:</hi> and as <hi>Philo</hi> goes on, Jam jam aſſumendus, &amp; in ipſis ſtans carce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, unde ad coeleſtem metam erat evolaturus, tunc quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> afflatus Divinitus vivens adhuc Prophetavit. He being <hi>yet alive, bleſſed all the tribes of Iſrael, and propheſied of their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proſperity,</hi> Deut. 33. Being now to go up into Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> and die, he went as from his <hi>Priſon</hi> to a <hi>Throne,</hi> and from a glimpſe of that <hi>earthly Canaan</hi> which he was deni'd to enter, to poſſeſs that <hi>heavenly Canaan</hi> which was open to receive him.</p>
            <p>Which brings us to the laſt part of our <hi>Parallel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> was like <hi>Moſes</hi> in his <hi>death</hi> alſo: for, <hi>ſo died Moſes the ſervant of the Lord in the land of Moab, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of the Lord.</hi> He began to die as a <hi>King,</hi> when <hi>Aaron the Saint of the Lord,</hi> his <hi>chief Miniſter</hi> about the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and <hi>the things belonging to the Worſhip of God,</hi> was violently pluckt from him, not for <hi>conſenting</hi> to, but for his endeavour to <hi>ſuppreſs</hi> thoſe <hi>golden Calves</hi> which <hi>the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had made,</hi> and <hi>ſet up to themſelves as their Gods,</hi> not to <hi>go before them towards Canaaa,</hi> but to <hi>lead them back to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> whither they were returning. He died on Mount <hi>Hor,</hi> the <hi>Tower-hill. Jethro</hi> alſo, his <hi>great Counſellor,</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him by the ſame <hi>bloudy hands.</hi> And the <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of the place where <hi>Moſes</hi> died, is very conſiderable in our <hi>Parallel:</hi> for he muſt <hi>go up from the plains of Moab, the land of his inheritance;</hi> (for ſo <hi>Moab</hi> ſignifieth <hi>de Patre,</hi> the Land which deſcended to him from his Fathers) to <hi>Mount Abarim,</hi> where ſtood the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Moab,</hi> and where the greateſt concourſe of people was: for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitus.</hi> Near <hi>Abarim</hi> ſtood the Hill <hi>Nebo,</hi> where was the <hi>Royal Palace:</hi> and adjoyning to that was the <hi>Vertix Piſgah,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101059:13"/>the <hi>Banqueting-houſe,</hi> where he had a <hi>proſpect</hi> of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which God had promiſed to give him as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; yet here <hi>die he muſt,</hi> not ſo much for his <hi>own</hi> ſins, as for the ſins of the <hi>people,</hi> who now had <hi>caſt off all fear of God,</hi> and <hi>what then ſhould a King do among them?</hi> Hoſea 10.3. But <hi>our Moſes muſt die</hi> (ſay the Rebel-people) <hi>according to the word of the Lord.</hi> Certainly there was no word of the <hi>Lord Jehovah,</hi> that the <hi>people</hi> ſhould put their <hi>King</hi> to death: it muſt be ſome <hi>enthuſiaſtick dream</hi> of an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuated ſpirit</hi> from <hi>the God of this world,</hi> that inſpired them with ſuch a <hi>Revelation.</hi> The word which God ſpake con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Moſes,</hi> (Deut. 32.49.) was onely this; <hi>Aſcende &amp; morere,</hi> Go up and die. He had an <hi>aſcention,</hi> even before his <hi>diſſolution:</hi> An <hi>aſcention</hi> I call it, becauſe God had promiſed (<hi>Exod.</hi> 33.14.) to <hi>go up with him,</hi> and to <hi>give him reſt;</hi> to <hi>gather him to his fathers,</hi> and <hi>hide him in the clifts of the rock</hi> until the <hi>ſtorm</hi> was over, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.22. So that though God had told him that it was a <hi>terrible thing that God would do with him,</hi> Exod. 34.10. yet having the preſence of an <hi>All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient God,</hi> with whom he might <hi>converſe as a man talketh with his friend face to face,</hi> Exod. 33.11. and having ſeen <hi>all the goodneſs of the Lord paſs before him, and proclaiming the Lord God to be gracious and merciful, long ſuffering, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in goodneſs and truth, forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion, and ſin, and that would by no means clear the guilty,</hi> Exod. 34.6, 7. this made the <hi>face of our Moſes to ſhine,</hi> even when that <hi>black vail</hi> was <hi>laid over it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now he gives <hi>inſtruction</hi> to his <hi>Succeſſor Joſhua,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Church and People of God;</hi> not doubting but that <hi>God,</hi> under his <hi>conduct,</hi> would bring that <hi>ſtiffnecked peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> into <hi>Canaan.</hi> And then with an <hi>undaunted courage,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſeth himſelf to his <hi>laſt Combat,</hi> being aſſured of <hi>victory</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>all his Enemies:</hi> and more like an <hi>Orator</hi> from his <hi>Desk,</hi> than a <hi>dying man</hi> on the <hi>Scaffold,</hi> he thus exhorteth the People, as it is recorded by <hi>Joſephus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101059:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I thought it requiſite, leſt I ſhould fail of my duty, to lay open the way that leadeth to your happineſs. Obey God, and keep his Laws, which I have given you, not innovating any thing in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Hearken to the counſel of</hi> Eleazar <hi>the Prieſt, and</hi> Joſhua <hi>my ſucceſſor, with the Senate. Be not ſtiff-necked, and think it not your liberty to mutiny againſt the commandments of your Prince. God forbid you ſhould be ſo exaſperated againſt them as againſt me: for I have been more often in hazard of my life by your means than by my enemies. I ſpeak not this to upbraid you, but to admoniſh you, and make you wiſer for the time to come, in obeying the Laws of your Country, in abhorring the Gods of the Nations, and adhering to the Religion in which I die. God having prefixed the day and place of my departure, I give him thanks, and ſubmit.</hi> And thus after <hi>mutual embraces</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and <hi>Eleazar</hi> the Prieſt, bleſſing the <hi>People,</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>himſelf</hi> and his <hi>enemies,</hi> he laid down his <hi>earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> his <hi>Crown of Thorns,</hi> and <hi>diſtracted Kingdoms,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an <hi>immarceſcible Crown of Glory,</hi> and <hi>a Kingdom that cannot be moved, eternal in the Heavens.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Os Domini.</note> And thus he <hi>died,</hi> as the <hi>Rabbins</hi> interpret the Text, with <hi>a kiſs of God's mouth;</hi> or <hi>according to the Word of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>exeunt Tyranni:</hi> His Murtherers having <hi>killed the Heir,</hi> they go and <hi>take poſſeſſion;</hi> but <hi>the Land ſpewed them out</hi> one after another, till <hi>Shiloh came,</hi> to whom it did belong. But as ſoon as the People had time to conſider their <hi>great loſs,</hi> and the Books of the <hi>Law</hi> written by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and left as a <hi>Legacy</hi> to the People, and were made ſenſible of the <hi>Rapine</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> of his Murtherers, <hi>they wept ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely,</hi> ſaith <hi>Joſephus; the men rent their clothes, the women beat their breaſts, and ſadneſs covered all faces;</hi> his very <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies</hi> being aſhamed of that <hi>Horrid Parricide. It was pity</hi> (ſaid ſome) <hi>his Conceſſions had not been better conſidered. Had he not been a King</hi> (ſaid others of them) <hi>he might have lived longer.</hi> And even thoſe who had <hi>betrayed</hi> and <hi>murthered</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:101059:14"/>him, would, like <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> have <hi>waſht their hands</hi> from his <hi>bloud,</hi> if it had been poſſible. The <hi>Actors</hi> in this <hi>Tragedy</hi> would ſtill keep themſelves <hi>as unknown</hi> as the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner. It was not we,</hi> ſay the <hi>Presbyterians; nor we,</hi> ſay the <hi>Independents:</hi> nor did the <hi>one</hi> deſtroy him as a <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> as a <hi>man;</hi> but <hi>both</hi> were <hi>Regicides,</hi> and <hi>both lift up their hands againſt the Lords Anointed.</hi> The <hi>London-Miniſters</hi> endeavoured, but in vain, to <hi>waſh their hands</hi> from that bloud: but their <hi>Vindication</hi> carrieth a <hi>Confutation</hi> with it: for they ſay, <hi>The woful Miſcarriages of the King himſelf, which we cannot but acknowledge to be many and very great in his Government, that have coſt the three Kingdoms ſo dear, and caſt him down from his Excellency into a horrid Pit of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery almoſt beyond example.</hi> Was this a more likely means to <hi>preſerve</hi> his life, or to <hi>deſtroy</hi> it? to charge him with all the <hi>miſeries</hi> of the late <hi>War.</hi> And a <hi>Leader</hi> of this Party ſays, that <hi>the removal of our Ceremonies onely, might counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail for all the Bloud and Treaſure ſpilt and ſpent in thoſe Diſtractions. Jenkins</hi> Sermon, <hi>Sept.</hi> 24. <hi>p.</hi> 23. which was ſpoken in 1656. about 8 years after the Kings death. They did not indeed erect <hi>a high Court of Juſtice</hi> to <hi>arraign</hi> him, but they <hi>raiſed Armies</hi> to <hi>fight</hi> againſt him: <hi>And it is to be believed</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) <hi>that a man would kill him whom he fights againſt.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Marſhal,</hi> p. 19. of a Letter of his, ſays, That <hi>if the King had been ſlain in battel, it had been none of the Parliaments fault: for he might have kept himſelf farther off if he pleaſed.</hi> And they might have kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>at home,</hi> and <hi>done their own buſineſs,</hi> and not the Devils work, in purſuing their King to his <hi>Priſon,</hi> which hath uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally been the <hi>Grave</hi> of Kings, as it was his. And in this the <hi>Army-men,</hi> in a Book called <hi>Bonds and Bounds,</hi> argued not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs: <hi>If by the Covenant</hi> (ſay they, <hi>p.</hi> 45.) <hi>we were indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly obliged to preſerve his</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Kings) <hi>Perſon, how comes it to paſs that we were obliged by the ſame Covenant to wage War againſt him? I have heard of a diſtinction between his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101059:15"/>Perſon and his Power, but never between his Perſon and Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. So that if the Covenant would have diſpenſed with any Souldier of</hi> England <hi>or</hi> Scotland <hi>to kill his perſon by an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of War</hi> (as his life was oft in <hi>danger,</hi> before he was brought to the <hi>Scaffold</hi>) <hi>his death had been violent, and the obligations to preſerve him had ended; and yet according to this argument, the Covenant had not been broken: why then ſhould theſe men think the World ſo dull, as not to underſtand plainly enough that the Covenant provided for his death more ways than one?</hi> And in brief, the Actions of the <hi>two Parties</hi> differed onely as <hi>Diminutio &amp; obtruncatio Capitis:</hi> They that took away his <hi>Regal Power,</hi> did <hi>diminuere caput Regis;</hi> they that took away his <hi>Life,</hi> did <hi>obtruncare Caput:</hi> they that firſt gave <hi>Commiſſion to raiſe a War</hi> againſt him, and they that <hi>ſlew</hi> him, were equally guilty; for they are all <hi>Principals</hi> in ſuch an <hi>execrable Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nec dum finitus Oreſtes.</hi> The immortal hatred of theſe perſons would not permit the dead body of <hi>Moſes</hi> to be <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered with his Fathers,</hi> and be <hi>at reſt:</hi> for we read in St. <hi>Jude,</hi> v. 9. of <hi>the Devil and his Angels diſputing with</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael <hi>and his Angels about the body of</hi> Moſes: either while it was yet <hi>alive,</hi> the Devil intending to ſend ſome <hi>evil Spirit</hi> to <hi>diſpatch him ſecretly,</hi> which the <hi>good Angels</hi> oppoſed; or being <hi>dead,</hi> to deny him a <hi>Burial-place</hi> with his <hi>Anceſtors;</hi> for the ſame reaſon perhaps that the <hi>Apoſtate Julian</hi> remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Bones of <hi>Babilas</hi> the Martyr, becauſe the <hi>Devils O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle</hi> could not aſſiſt him while the <hi>Martyr</hi> lay ſo near it: and therefore he muſt be buried at a <hi>diſtance</hi> in the <hi>Valley,</hi> leſt the <hi>Regicides</hi> ſhould be minded of their <hi>guilt,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> inraged at the remembrance of their <hi>loſs.</hi> But as <hi>Pliny, de viris Illuſtribus,</hi> ſpeaking how the <hi>Romans</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed to revenge the death of <hi>Romulus</hi> their Founder, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi> ſtept forth and ſaid to them, <hi>Be not troubled, O ye Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, for I ſaw your King in a glorious Chariot aſcending up into Heaven:</hi> So, to allay our <hi>ſorrows,</hi> and to cauſe us to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101059:15"/>lay aſide all thoughts of <hi>revenge,</hi> I ſay, his Enemies have ſo far kept their words with him, as to <hi>make him a glorious King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus fell the <hi>beſt of Kings</hi> by the <hi>worſt of men,</hi> that had generally <hi>ſworn Allegiance to him,</hi> and often <hi>perjured them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> by <hi>Covenants</hi> and <hi>Engagements againſt him.</hi> He fell before his <hi>own Palace,</hi> and at the <hi>Gates</hi> of his <hi>great,</hi> but <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relenting City.</hi> He fell in <hi>the midſt of his Age,</hi> and <hi>maturity of his Strength,</hi> and <hi>fulneſs of Grace,</hi> the Prodigy of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Meekneſs:</hi> He fell by the <hi>Sword,</hi> and for the ſins of a <hi>ſtiff-necked</hi> and <hi>rebellious People.</hi> He fell not alone, but our <hi>Religion,</hi> our <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> fell with him: and out of the <hi>Aſhes</hi> of that <hi>Phaenix,</hi> they all <hi>roſe again,</hi> and reſumed their firſt <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>ſplendour.</hi> If we number him among the <hi>good Kings,</hi> none of them was <hi>ſo wiſe;</hi> if among the <hi>wiſe,</hi> none of them was <hi>ſo good. Charles le Bon</hi> was not <hi>ſo wiſe,</hi> nor <hi>Charlemain</hi> was ever <hi>ſo good.</hi> If the names of all the <hi>beſt Princes</hi> were to be engraved in a Ring, the name of <hi>this King</hi> would ſerve as a <hi>Diamond</hi> to give vertue and luſter to it. <hi>Carolus Primus nulli Secundus;</hi> his <hi>Murther</hi> therefore was a Murther (all circumſtances conſidered) not to be parallel'd by any but the <hi>Paſſion</hi> of <hi>our great Lord</hi> and <hi>common Saviour;</hi> and, next to that, to be <hi>deteſted</hi> and <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred</hi> of all men.</p>
            <p>And this is the firſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Concluſion</hi> that I ſhall draw from theſe <hi>Premiſes;</hi> That we ſeriouſly <hi>lament</hi> and <hi>repent</hi> for thoſe <hi>Impieties</hi> which the ſins of the Nation drew upon it ſelf, and from which the Land <hi>is not purged to this day.</hi> For as God threatned <hi>Iſrael</hi> for the ſin of <hi>making the golden Calves,</hi> that when he <hi>viſited,</hi> he would <hi>viſit that ſin</hi> upon them; from whence the <hi>Jews</hi> obſerved, that <hi>in every judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there was an ounce</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſome greater weight for the ſin) <hi>of the golden Calf:</hi> So we may juſtly believe, that by thoſe <hi>dreadful Plagues</hi> and <hi>Conflagrations</hi> that have been on the <hi>Land,</hi> and eſpecially on the <hi>great City,</hi> God would <hi>call to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101059:16"/>our remembrance</hi> that <hi>great ſin</hi> for which <hi>his anger is not yet turned away, but his wrath is ſtretched out ſtill.</hi> And becauſe <hi>amendment of life</hi> is the beſt ſigne of <hi>Repentance,</hi> let us imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate his Example in <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>peaceableneſs of Spirit,</hi> in <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> in <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> even to our <hi>greateſt Enemies;</hi> but eſpecially in his Love to <hi>that Church</hi> which <hi>adhered ſo faithfully to him,</hi> and which therefore he <hi>ſo loved,</hi> as to <hi>lay down his life for it;</hi> and in whoſe <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> if you keep your ſelves, you will be free from that <hi>great iniquity</hi> of <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> which are <hi>like the ſin of Witchcraft.</hi> Which word minds me of one <hi>Admonition</hi> more, That you would conſider the nature of <hi>this ſin,</hi> which comes ſo nigh to the ſin of <hi>Witchcraſt,</hi> that it <hi>ſeldom admits</hi> of any <hi>repentance:</hi> for a <hi>ſad obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and yet <hi>too true</hi> it is, that among all the <hi>Regicides</hi> that were executed for that <hi>actual Murther</hi> of the <hi>Father</hi> (which how horrid it was, you have heard) and among thoſe that died for the <hi>intended Murther</hi> of the <hi>Son,</hi> whom God long preſerve! though they all <hi>acknowledged</hi> or were <hi>proved</hi> guilty of the <hi>Fact,</hi> not one <hi>repented</hi> of the ſin, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that God hath <hi>threatned ſuch reſiſtance with damnation:</hi> and though ſuch may eſcape the judgment of <hi>men,</hi> it will be <hi>a fearful thing</hi> for them in their impenitency <hi>to fall into the hands of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us be careful of being <hi>corrupted</hi> by <hi>ſuch Principles</hi> as will lead us directly to the practice of <hi>Rebellion;</hi> as, That there is any earthly Power <hi>above</hi> or <hi>co-ordinate</hi> with the King, whether it be that of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Conclave,</hi> or that of the <hi>Presbyter</hi> and his <hi>Conſiſtory,</hi> or that of the <hi>People</hi> and their <hi>Repreſentatives;</hi> as if the <hi>Original</hi> of the <hi>Kingly Authority</hi> were in them, and they might <hi>give</hi> or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſume</hi> it as they pleaſe: That the <hi>King,</hi> though he be <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis major,</hi> yet he is <hi>univerſis minor:</hi> That <hi>Dominion is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Grace;</hi> on which Maxime, as a <hi>Popiſh Prince</hi> may be <hi>cut off</hi> by his <hi>Proteſtant Subjects,</hi> ſo a <hi>Proteſtant Prince</hi> may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101059:16"/>be <hi>cut off</hi> by his <hi>Popiſh Subjects:</hi> and then as often as any <hi>jealous, ſeduced,</hi> or <hi>diſcontented Subjects</hi> ſhall judge, or be perſwaded, that their Prince is of a <hi>different Perſwaſion</hi> from themſelves in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> they may think it lawful to reſiſt him: and ſo, no <hi>King</hi> nor <hi>Government</hi> in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom can be <hi>ſecure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Take heed alſo of entring into <hi>Covenants, Aſſociations,</hi> and <hi>Engagements, without and againſt the King:</hi> from <hi>theſe,</hi> as from the <hi>Trojan Horſe,</hi> whole <hi>Armies</hi> have iſſued out.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Take heed alſo of being perſwaded that your <hi>former Oaths</hi> and <hi>Obligations</hi> to Obedience are <hi>diſſolved,</hi> by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>new Vows</hi> and <hi>Covenants;</hi> which would <hi>vacuate</hi> all <hi>Oaths of Fidelity</hi> between men, and make them as <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſon's Withs,</hi> to be broken at pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Take heed of that <hi>keen diſtinction,</hi> which divides be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Kings Perſon</hi> and his <hi>Power,</hi> and teacheth that it is lawful <hi>by his authority to fight againſt his Perſon,</hi> contrary to the Law of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Land;</hi> and of all thoſe <hi>other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes</hi> which the famous Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> hath <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> and <hi>burnt,</hi> as tending to <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Beware of all thoſe <hi>ſeditious ſuggeſtions</hi> of <hi>diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, ambitious</hi> and <hi>factious</hi> men, that do inſinuate <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies</hi> and <hi>ſuſpitions</hi> of <hi>evil Government,</hi> and labour to make <hi>Parties</hi> and raiſe <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Corah</hi> raiſed againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Abſolon</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel</hi> againſt <hi>David:</hi> for from hence come <hi>murmurings,</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking evil of Dignities, Strife and Envyings, bitter Zeal and Contentions, Wars and Fightings, Confuſions, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very evil thing.</hi> And take the more heed of thoſe things at <hi>this time</hi> eſpecially, when there are as yet ſome of the <hi>old Incendiaries</hi> kindling the Coals of <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and leading multitudes of <hi>ſeduced Souls</hi> ſtep by ſtep into thoſe <hi>ways</hi> and <hi>methods</hi> which ended in our late <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> and would carry us head-long a ſecond time into <hi>the ſame Confuſions.</hi> I conclude with <hi>Solomon</hi>'s advice: <q>
                  <hi>My ſon, fear
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101059:17"/>thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change: for their calamity ſhall come upon them ſuddenly; and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</hi> 
                  <bibl>Prov. 24.22.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And one point of <hi>Charity</hi> more I ſhall commend, as moſt ſeaſonable at <hi>this time,</hi> which may help to <hi>imbalm</hi> the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> and cauſe our <hi>Prayers</hi> to <hi>aſcend as Incenſe,</hi> by joyning our <hi>Alms</hi> with them; that as we ſeek to <hi>break off our ſins by repentance,</hi> ſo we would <hi>purge out our iniquities by giving to the poor,</hi> whoſe <hi>number</hi> and <hi>neceſſities</hi> the hand of God in this <hi>Extream Weather</hi> hath increaſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us. Methinks I hear them crying to us, <hi>Give ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for King</hi> Charles <hi>his ſake.</hi> And our <hi>Liberality</hi> at this time will be ſuch a teſtimony of our <hi>Religious affection</hi> to the memory of that <hi>good King,</hi> as <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi>'s Oyntment which ſhe poured on Chriſt's head, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.12. <hi>She hath wrought a good work; in that ſhe poured out this oyntment on my body, ſhe did it for my burial.</hi> And if we be <hi>ready to do good, willing to communicate,</hi> we are aſſured that <hi>with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
